hello I'm higher to sign okay so just
one second I'll just make sure it's
going it's all good
right
welcome to both
it is
June 13th at zero UTC we're here in
active guest stream number 44.1 with
hayato saiko and nasugu suchia so really
looking forward to this presentation and
discussion hayato please um say hello
and then we'll continue with nasuku's
presentation
hello I'm hayatussago I'm a
mathematician and mathematical physicist
also interested in Consciousness and a
real working I work I have worked a lot
with uh Now
by using category Theory and application
to IIT or other Consciousness Series so
now
all right so uh my name is now tutia I'm
a professor in Monash University and
also uh having a lab in ATR in Japan and
other sort of the introduction to this
today's session I'll give a brief talk
on our recent project called the Korea
structure which uh python I will be
collaborating and also a little bit on
the quantum Courier hypothesis
uh both of them are hopefully relevant
to active inference uh issue
so uh
the the quota structure project is the
Japanese funding that we received
recently and uh it's going to continue
for five years uh this will be uh to
establish a super interdisciplinary
research program to tackle the program
of Consciousness especially qualia
through the interdisciplinary research
and we are planning to also host a
summer school for two to three weeks
every year
and here's the ah fantastic members for
this uh Grand and hayato is uh basically
uh
working with me to uh uh in the part of
the mathematical approach to the
Consciousness and the Korea
and uh uh so one of the program for
example we want to address is for
example when you see this uh Square uh
Daniel what do you see here
blue
yeah so you say blue and I say maybe AO
in Japanese and the height of may say
Russian uh
mean the same experience Gloria but how
do we know that we are actually
experiencing the same thing
and I I'm actually curious whether this
kind of question is something that free
energy or active inference kind of style
approach can ever tackle that my
Approach is to go into the category
Theory kind of inspired uh Direction and
here's the
first study that published out uh you
know we publishing a few years ago with
uh
ayato and the Shigeru together with also
the another category theorist Steve
Phillips
that in category Theory there's an
interesting Lemma called the unitarama
that proves that all the relationship
characterize its internal intrinsic
property and we are using that idea to
study The Courier
that's the kind of an inspiration of our
approach so instead of you know trying
to characterize what the Brew is or red
is we are trying to
um characterize all the relationship
between a particular color or particular
Korea to other
exorcery and then by finding the
correspondence of this relationship we
try to identify uh what the actual blue
is
so if you will say blue is similar to
Green but and also similar to Red then
that's going to be very different from
my group and that's the way how we you
know detect this you know blueness is
same or different
and uh one recent application of this
kind of idea is this uh
unsupervised alignment uh that we are
using with another collaborative muscle
for me always mean University Tokyo and
I'll skip the detail but basically what
we are doing
is to do some kind of experiment and
then collect a lot of data to obtain uh
so-called similarity Matrix between all
the colors and then uh Without Really
knowing what color maps onto what we try
to use on the relationship to predict
what we are seeing so in a sense this is
a purely category theoretical kind of
you know approach to uh the program of
consciousness
so then I'll just skip uh the details
here
and then uh
uh yeah so we are doing this kind of
approach on other types of Aquaria and
then this is the thing that we are
planning to do for Wow next five years
and then
that another just brief kind of you know
introduction if you have some other uh
question uh we can come back later so
this is potentially more to do with that
active inference aspect of our approach
in a sense and this is called the
quantum Courier hypothesis uh we we
published this uh preprint really
recently and so you can access it later
so um one of the uh there are many
programs in the current you know uh
models of the quality or Consciousness
where we tend to think that um
experience or Consciousness is like you
know one point in the high dimensional
space and we use that kind of idea for
our previous you know alignment
experiment uh approach but uh
it lacks Dynamics and it also lacks the
you know effects that we uh tend to
experience where you know the
observation or report or introspection
itself sometimes change our quality
right
and um that's the sort of the active
inference aspect that I'm talking about
you know
um attention or introspection changes
about experience
but the traditional approach is very
difficult to deal with this and one way
to deal with that is this uh
uh Quantum formalism that we think uh is
appropriate so here we think that you
know there is some kind of Gloria
experiencing system that is defined as
this blue boundary you can consider that
as sort of the mark of blanket like
thing
in the free energy kind of idea
and then we consider a particular type
of the quail like redness a balloon as
itself as an observable it's a
terminology in quantum theory uh
something that in principle can be
observed within this Warrior
and then we consider this measurement as
a process that probe this accordions um
you know observable
and unlike a classical uh favorite
theoretical thinking we think that the
measurement or probing of this
observable
through it's called a state changes its
you know States and also observable
itself
and that's something that we can
actually formalize mathematically using
a concept called a very general concept
of this uh conditional probability
called the instruments it's a it's very
technical for the you know uh quick talk
so I'll leave it but you know this is a
modern Quantum uh theoretical idea that
captures both you know how we can uh
affect on the world and the the quota
itself can be affected by that
measurement and then using this we think
that you know um uh we can explain
properly Korea in a much more reasonable
way with the mathematics
and uh solver it's just a kind of theory
but we already think that it's probably
better than the existing kind of a model
of the for example attention and
Consciousness and also uh
it also uh provides some kind of you
know prediction and the explanation of
why
some of the two concepts or two
experience can feel different uh
depending on the order that you
experience
so this is just like conceptual kind of
example
but if I ask you Danielle that uh is
China similar to North Korea
then you might say probably
no right
I I don't even know the reference point
yeah okay but let's say you know just
objectively you know China doesn't feel
similar to North Korea okay
yeah however if I reverse the order it's
not North Korea similar to China
then many people actually start to say
that ah yeah it's kind of similar
does that have to do with one being
larger or what is it about the order
that primes people to respond
differently
yeah so many people have already you
know come up came up with many different
kind of ideas to to explain this kind of
individual aspects of this you know
older effects
but as we uh mentioned you know we are
actually Computing or you know measuring
this kind of order effects
systematically through all combinations
of the colors for example
there it's hard to systematically
explain why this other effect emerges in
One cases but not the other and in which
direction right
but well that's what we found basically
and but using this in a Quantum
cognition kind of framework we can
explain it really nicely
in this case it's just a projection post
rate but uh we are probably going to
extend much more in the more instrument
like you know a framework in the future
yeah so
and also we can we are also predicting
that there may be some kind of well uh
violation like uh a violation of value
inequality like situation in uh you know
uh perception and if we can confirm that
that also you know gives a Credence to
our proposal that the quality is like
you know it needs to be uh framed or
explained in the quantum framework
so I think that's probably enough to uh
start up the conversation I guess
awesome
okay
great
lot to uh jump into all
uh share my screen so we can take
some notes
okay
um how so do you want to give a first
remark or I'm happy to but but do you
have a first remark or what parts of the
work do you want to reflect on first
foreign
[Music]
I think maybe the categorical approach
the importance of the categorical
approach is one issue to talk uh
uh with you I think because uh you first
pointed out that uh paper uh with
Shigeru taguchi in 2016.
um so I'm uh interested in why you and
uh
your colleague are interested in that
paper from the active inference side so
can you explain some feeling or
foreign yes
so this is
um
using category Theory to assess the
relationship between Consciousness and
integrated information Theory with the
two of you and taguchi from 2016. so
um
I've long been interested in scale free
or scale independent ways to describe
systems and information theory has been
recognized as one of those approaches
and information theory has been proposed
to not just play of course a central
role in the functionality of information
systems but with IIT and related
theorems to also strike at the heart of
the most
quintessential aspect of our conscious
experience so that seems like an
incredible
synthesis of the functionality of
systems that don't necessarily seem to
have anything quality alike at all
merely performing calculations like a
super fast Abacus basically
um and
so I am curious and feel free to address
either of these things
when we describe Information Systems
what is it that would or could or is uh
experienced are they experiencing their
the their information what they are
processing or what is it about
information integration would Grant a
system the ability to move Beyond a
behavioral functionality into again
strike at the heart of one of the most
ineffable questions that the mind can
really consider
um
okay interesting
um actually the category itself uh in
mathematics originated are created in
mid-20s centuries uh to bridge the two
different fields that is uh geometry and
algebra uh more specifically the
topology you know something about what
was you maybe
um which is a very uh General kind of uh
mathematical methods to capture the
essence of the figures uh for like a
circle or the complicated uh figures and
the the fundamental program or the
topology is you can you
identify the two different uh figures
essentially that means you can can you
transform continuously to the other
figures or not so if the one figure goes
to other figure with A continuous
transformation and back then it is uh
viewed as essentially the same but the
two the screen to to determine the two
figures there's chances are the same is
a very difficult question
so
um like great mathematician right
figured out the utility of the algebraic
methods that like making the one figure
to the other uh from the figure you can
construct the algebraic system like
groups or something
and then
the uh the transform uh the problem into
the algebraic region
the then the point is very essential
point is uh
taking one figure to the uh the uh
constructing one algebra from the one
figure is not sufficient the point is
the deviation should be transformed the
the other regions so one region here
other regions here but one two one
correspondence of object is not surface
entry but the relations if you can
transform the older relations into the
other regions then you can uh provide uh
you can prove something from one region
to another region because uh yeah this
is a notion of the fact uh like the
region intuitively I talked about the
term using term the region it is
mathematically called category category
it consists of objects and arrows arrows
or amorphism which is a generic kind of
relationship between these objects so
our topological region is some kind of
category of topology like a top that
objects the topological space and the
continuous functions continuous mapping
is a role or something the other regions
we can for example as a recreation like
groups and group homorphism or the
module Vector space or something so
something RJ rack and the relationship
between them so category is uh defined
to formulate the uh intuitive concept of
bridging something function so first the
Arenberg and Mark brain defined category
to Define this notion of function by the
bridging to region then if this is
established then you can infer about the
topological reasons category by using
the algebraic the relation or something
so we uh that is now on shiger and me uh
talked about the possible application of
this kind of argument into the
um uh conscious and study that it is
just a problem of bridging different
kind of regions like uh physically uh
testable religion under our role
experience itself or something so it is
apollia it seems appear it is a two
difficult question too hard problem to
connect to these decisions but if you
only focus on the object but the
relationship if you can compare the
relationship then you can infer
something about you cannot
directly touch you directly manipulate
so this is the idea
yeah maybe I'll just add a little bit
um so uh yeah as I had said oh you know
under you you are taking really diligent
notes so that may be uh quite good but
uh I from my end uh so this uh
paper was inspired by really talking to
um
Shigeru and the meeting in this summer
school on Consciousness and there I met
I encountered in this in a category
theory for the first time
and uh
there were several shocking kind of you
know uh
Concepts that I learned from this link
first encounter one is that you know
there isn't a way to compare two
completely different things and then
extract the common structure between
them at a higher to first introduced me
this you know very strong strange paper
which I didn't understand at all but was
so interesting that I could read you
know for hours and hours it's called the
Rosetta Stone it points out uh
commonality between the topology quantum
physics logic and computation
yeah
yeah that was the title and then I
didn't understand what the heck is this
in a paper but uh
that's that uses this category Theory
and uh as a whole I feel like ah I see
so maybe if we understand the structure
behind this each of this a concrete
example we may be able to find a
commonality or explanation at that level
and that naturally applied to my you
know program at the time which is you
know how to bridge the gap between the
Korea and the information structure
derived from neural you know uh activity
this is this looks also completely
different but if there is any
possibility to bridge the gap
it must be some kind of structure or
mathematics and that's this category
Theory
hello one point is uh one other point is
that you know you I I I think you uh you
can get the ideas and functions by
breathing the two regions then the
really interesting thing another really
interesting concept is called natural
transformation natural transformation is
the uh kind of deformation or
transformation between transformation so
you imagine some Theory Bridges some
addition to the another region so there
is a one meta level Arrow code
but uh another theory uh predicts
another thing or something but can you
connect these theories or models this is
a problem of natural transformation
so one representation one Theory or
something uh uh May map the one region
to another region but there is a there
may be another
various kind of mappings functors so the
problem is to compare or to unite to
connect this transformation is a
functions is called natural transmission
if the function is naturally isomorphic
that means there is a reversible natural
transformation between functors then uh
these Essence these series seems
different but essentially the same so
kind of natural transformation is maybe
the hint to connect to the various
series on Consciousness or something and
also the our Consciousness experiences
itself will be connected to the concept
of natural transformation because
the I see something that the different
thing something but there is no uh
divided discrete kind of construction
but there are some continuous or
relating something so this is this view
view is something that like function the
another view is something like function
but there is no division there is some
relationship so our experience maybe uh
itself a kind of product of uh natural
transformation like yeah maybe now can
you you can explain like a peripheral
oh maybe
ah no you're muted muted
is it all right if I draw some kind of
figure oh of course would you like to
share your screen
yeah and also if you can give me the
access to you know uh to The annotation
okay
um I will
um make it so everyone can edit and I'll
put it into the
chat here and then also if you want to
draw that would be awesome
yeah thank you now looks good yeah so
just to kind of recap what the Hyatt was
talking about is that uh we we tend to
think about something like a category
and then another uh category is there
and then there is some kind of object
which which could be quite uh you know
abstract and then it's related by Arrow
like this
and then if this category C is uh
somehow possible to map onto this
category D
while kind of preserving this you know
um arrow for example this arrow goes to
here and this arrow goes to here and
then each object is also you know
preserved then it's much more than the
usual kind of idea of a function between
the sets right because it also impose
the you know correspondence between the
relationship
[Music]
and in our idea basically if this is
let's say Gloria of the category and if
this is a neural uh activity or uh maybe
information domain and then maybe you
know we can have a background force of
the functor that would be great
usually uh the most of the mathematical
Theory Of Consciousness tries to go from
here to here right let's say in the case
of IIT
Arrow here and then what what Hyatt was
kind of talking uh in a way as a natural
transformation
is uh this
kind of you know secondary level Arrow
let's say I don't know whether free
energy or
active inference can uh count as a
prediction from you know neural activity
to the particular query but let's say if
there is something like that and then
maybe there is some kind of a
translation between these two theories
yeah if that exists that's called a
natural transformation
awesome well a few comments on this the
idea of
mapping the maps between the spaces is
so important it reminds me of metaphor
where we're conveying relationships and
saying well it's it's like a hammer or
it is a hammer for this other situation
so that's how we get few shot learning
and applicability and how we grasp
Concepts is perhaps developmentally or
from an evolutionary perspective in a
large extent by generalizing our spatial
and embodied understandings and then
certainly communication if you want to
have some semantics that are being
communicated across Minds through an
interface through a classical interface
then certainly you want the structure to
be preserved and then I think the one
that you have here is one of the most
provocative for those empirically
studying
uh consciousness
because it's kind of like this side is
empirical
and let's just say we don't know what
the Q side is for now but let's just say
it's another space that isn't that
and then
if there is a certain uh landscape that
neural activity patterns flow through
like some kind of winterless competition
or you get some sort of limit cycle and
you find that there's a limit cycle of
neural activity and then there's also uh
that is being paralleled by experiential
Cycles
then that is not just an accounting
system that's a very strong
finding about potentially the real
underlying causal system especially
because it can suggest unique other
explanations or manipulations to make
right
do you want to mention anything about
the metaphor
yeah
before that uh very hard to say the
technical remark is that the for the
original uh problem that connects
um
topology and algebra then in that case
the algebra is more concrete more
manipulatable in that case and the
topology is something mysterious in this
case so in general the function is a
kind of
um generation the mapping in sets so the
something mysterious into something
concrete so
now the picture C and D should be
switched maybe in that case and yeah but
uh of course there is a background maybe
back and forth so the idea is
this our you are brew and my Brew
program is for example you can prove
that you can uh your blue and my Brew is
different if
there's something uh informational or
something the detectable structure is
completely different they are you brew
and micro is different of course you
cannot uh uh prove this the sameness
between you your blue and uh my Brew uh
if there is no how to say the back and
force function but even if you don't
have the uh the backwards function at
least you can demonstrate that your blue
and my Brew is different seems to be
different if the correspondence is
factorial or something so it is a big
step from The Experience answer site
that and with me and colleagues uh do
such a thing so you have my my your but
the this is not uh by focusing you
approve my Brew only but your blue read
something or you don't have to say even
do not have to say the name of something
so just uh
how to say no labeling for example but
the relations you you can teach the
relationship at these things you can
teach the relationship with these things
so then compare that so very
interestingly uh in general the
structure is surprisingly uh uh coherent
uh between persons proper persons or
yeah so it is very nice and also maybe
it's it's suggesting that the
non-isomorphic case
then you are blue and my Brew is
something different or something so I
think this approach is very interesting
even if
um in the no bi-directional Only One
Direction then but even that case it is
useful yeah it is my remark
yeah please please and then I'll have a
question about your drawing right so
this is a one of the slides that I
didn't show today but uh uh what what
hayat was talking about is um you know
kind of you know explaining this figure
like uh the way you experience red is
related to with the other experience uh
you know not only color but shape and
also with sound and so on in a very very
complicated way and then we can actually
measure how similar they are by asking
the people and then you can also do that
for the other people
and then these these two similarity
Matrix can be directly compared with our
you know new method of this unsupervised
learning and also IIT for example may
allow us in in the future to go back and
forth between these you know uh scoria
structure and the information structure
and then mathematically we believe that
the information structure the
information structure should be
potential you know translatable in some
way
and if that is possible in some way you
know eventually we may be able to say ah
okay so the way you are experiencing red
is
same or different in this way or that
way that that's a sort of the idea
can you go back to your drawing
right
awesome
so
the top Arrow as if we're kind of just
exploring what what might it mean that
IIT is going back and forth and also
that active inference is going back and
forth so what exactly does the edge
between C and D represent in IIT is that
a quantitative evaluation like the five
variable or what is being accounted for
with that Arrow
mm-hmm
do you want to say something yeah uh
there is a various possibilities
actually for example the sameness was
different or so if you have some kind of
uh
graduation with sameness so
yeah same as graduation but to a former
to to formulate The Graduate
gradation gradation of uh sameness you
have to move on the air reached category
not a simple kind of category but it's a
generalized kind of category called
enriched category in that case for
example the simplest example of enriched
category is a generalized General sorry
generalized Matrix space metric but the
like uh
in Matrix space for example the uh
the point p and p itself has a distance
zero of course and uh kind of P to q q
to R uh is uh there is a triangular
inequality or something so yeah then it
can be considered as a generalized kind
of uh compositional structure called
enriched category it is a typical kind
of in this category uh
so but the symmetry does not uh always
hold or something so this is a one how
to say the uh one small step to uh
grasp the our Courier structure because
uh like uh
now pointed out North Korea China
distance and the China North Korea
distance is uh in general different or
something so almost all studies uh
assume that some symmetry but we need to
go go uh beyond that
and then
maybe the one number or something is too
poor to represent everything so more you
have to go more and more richer
structure like not just numbers but some
kind of projection operator or something
then you enter into the quantum region
so
relationships we feel should we maybe
should be uh represented from the some
kind of the
relationship between the notion of State
in kind of quantum
Theory under State transition between
that so our approach is step by step and
you can choose the many arrows to study
something under something and then goes
to unify the more and more General kind
of arrows and categories and I this is
just for the speculation but this kind
of quantum theory theoretical like other
mathematical framework and not do not
need to that kind of physics but they're
called mathematics can you use unify
these kind of things
awesome but just a few comments on on
that
when we're doing free energy
minimization we use the KL Divergence
which is very importantly not a distance
because a distance would have the
Symmetry characteristic and so the KL is
chosen because it's easy to fit uh
optimization
on these variational distributions but
it's almost like it's a feature not a
bug that the KL Divergence between q and
P is not the same as p and Q
because it turns out that that that kind
of a of a divergence-based
um uh
quantification
actually has some advantages
um over a distance measure and then the
mapping between observables and hidden
States
and the cognitive operators that we
bring to bear on that kind of mapping
problem those are some of the most
fundamental pieces of the partially
observable Markov decision processes
that are used in the active inference
generative model which is first the
mapping between observables and hidden
States and then how do hidden States
change through time and how does Action
selection policy selection influence how
hidden States unfold Through Time
so this
mapping between hidden States and
observables in between hidden States and
the hidden State at the next time points
are and how again how action influences
that
if you understand those operations
then it's like a game of chess and the
ball just rolls downhill and the
variational distribution Works
exceedingly well but when those are off
base
then you're fitting your way like right
off a cliff
so uh maybe again I'll just add one uh
more points so you you asked uh in the
original like five minutes ago wow what
this you know each of these points or
Arrow
correspond to in the case of the IIT uh
and so on and then this is kind of uh
related to all these uh ideas but uh
well one of the
um you know fundamental uh insights uh
from IIT but also from philosophy
especially uh some kind of philosophy
called the process theory is uh it is uh
important to really understand that the
process of law or movement is really
fundamentally
um important kind of aspects of things
and then um that may be really
distinguishing some kind of static set
or
um the thing
uh in the static world and when they
start to interact and then when the
process emerged then something uh starts
to
potentially you know uh generate or
support subjective quality like you know
uh protocol kind of thing
and in the case of the IID uh it is uh
deeply kind of you know uh entrenched in
this you know formation of that
transition probability Matrix
of an entity like how this thing neuron
or logic gate
it might have come from the previous
state and it may go into the next state
so any kind of a moment is already
embedding the possible previous and the
possible future there is some kind of a
with us in a moment because it's a
process
and when the process is considered then
you know as I have said that you know
this kind of you know dot is a very you
know kind of you know two Thin kind of
structure to think about so we need more
elaborated structure of a DOT itself but
the category theory is great uh in a
sense that each dot can itself contain
complicated structure it's just you know
wow
uh represented as a single dot but it
can't contain something more
right so the in an upshot one dot could
correspond to a collection of the
neuronal you know States and the
connectivity pattern and things like
that which can go from one to the other
and then that may that this kind of
movement May correspond to something
like you know we see redness or whatever
in this way but that's also with respect
to our other kind of you know arrows as
well and that that's the thought that
the wave of the relationship that we are
trying to characterize both in the
domain but Aquarius but also brain is
also the wave of the relationship
gigantic ones right
and as you said that you know transition
from one state to the another state
that's pretty much like dynamical State
uh that dynamical system like you know
approach
and then uh the simple idea called a
monoid is uh
applicable to this kind of dynamical
system approach uh correct me higher
though if I'm saying something you know
out of the bounds of my comfort zone but
uh you know any kind of a state can
transition into another state and then
this tradition itself can be represented
by the arrow
[Music]
and uh yeah so uh and that kind of the
combination of that particular kind of
Arrow composition May correspond to one
experience
so that that's uh uh one thing I wanted
to say the other thing that I had also
one uh it was then mentioned about
Observer brand states and why we are
interested in the quantum uh you know
framework quantum theory by the way it's
not a Quantum brain hypothesis we are
not saying that you know Quantum you
know phenomena in the brain is critical
for Consciousness but it's just a
mathematical structure of the quantum
theory that is important to understand
the Korea
and the essence is most likely to be
this you know non-commutativity
[Music]
any kind of process that you do like you
know cooking you know putting the water
and then uh model is different from
model and then putting water right
and so any kind of process we do there's
some kind of you know temporal
dependency the commutativity doesn't
hold and that's also probably the case
for the Korea
and if that's the case uh then
for you maybe it's a bit surprising but
you know Bayesian kind of statistics and
Beijing probability
may not work as you might wish
yes
so the in other words using the counter
mathematics the there is a quite good
generalization of Bayesian uh
Innovation or
Vision kind of
uh inference yes uh actually the the the
the
one step generalization is called the
projection uh in kind of mathematics
that are then there is more
generalization code uh instruments so
instrument is a general notion of
measurements like a system and the
environments uh interacting the then
more precisely the measurement is
something that like the interaction
feature has some probe over their uh
apparatus so probe is some kind of the
yeah
the the
apparatus is some very small tips or
something which can be considered as a
Quantum that this Quantum system and
this probe system interacting randomly
then we can measure this probe by the
macro side or the apparatus so this is a
very general kind of uh measurement uh
which is called which is identified
mathematical with the notion over uh
instrument originated by the Davis and
Lewis and the uzalar one of our
collaborators
we begin in the cooperation but other uh
who is also famous for the ozawas in
inequality although inequality as a
generalization of the Heisenberg
University version of heist making
important but uh he uh identified that
this General notion measurement and
instrument called completely positive in
instruments in mathematics but this CP
completely positive instruments is a
quite General and
generalizing the very beautifully the
Bayesian
influence into the quantum side so I
think the the using and focusing this
kind of instrument kind of concept is
the key maybe the three uh to bridge the
um active Independence side on our side
and Quantum side or something so yeah it
is my speculation but I think it is very
fruitful Direction
oh it's awesome just one comment on that
the the probe with the instrument or the
quantum reference frame I believe as
Chris Fields might describe it
is an experimenter's choice and so
the way that we could talk about policy
selection and inference on which
experiment to run would be in terms of
which sequence of observations is going
to minimize expected free energy okay so
to have high pragmatic value and
epistemic value that's the expected free
energy functional now as researchers we
might seek out the most informative
experiments and not prefer to see a
certain measurement so we can say well
all measurements are a priori equally
pragmatically valuable to us so now
expected free energy is going to be
driven by information
maximization just by pure learning but
this recognition that action is woven in
to the process of reducing uncertainty
about
other systems across blankets
it's it's absolutely fundamental because
if you don't have the constraint that
you need to actively select which
experiments to run and to probe and to
interfere in this Quantum way this way
described by Quantum mathematics you're
kind of in a delusional alternative
world where like you get information
from photons but you don't have a sensor
so it's not an empirically tractable
World unless we take on this
constraints and then once we do our
mathematics
are the quantum mathematics and again
it's kind of a subtle point this isn't
the orc or this isn't necessarily
taking a stance one way or the other on
what kinds of electronic scale Quantum
phenomena exists in any system but
rather just sees Quantum mathematics as
fundamental to decision making and
uncertainty
which is quite a change from how it's
been discussed for a hundred years
actually
um
yeah as now said we are not um depending
on the hypothesis like uh there is a
Quantum physical process Behind The
Courier but the why we can uh use the
quantum mathematics is very very uh
simple reason
because a conventional probability
Theory practical probability Theory uh
depend on the probability space
classical one is too narrow to capture
for example over effect or something but
you can generalize it so kind of
mathematics is just generalized the
classical mathematics and I think I
believe that the
why Quantum mathematics is found for
kind of physics is very simple reason
because in classical physics the some
kind of the
um
determinism the classical determinism
is a very Universal on the
the probability only comes from the some
kind of inner ignorance of us but in
Quantum physical
context there is some kind of very
fundamental uh randomness of the
fundamental uh
accidents or something is found and they
are all surprised because if you go into
the micro side the determinism should be
stronger and stronger they thought but
actually there needs some kind there
they're found fundamental
non-commutativity and macro micro side
there was some people pointed out that
uh
Even In classical or evening sorry a
microscopic side but uh this kind of uh
the importance of non-commutativity is
very Universal not especially in micro
side but it is a historical reason that
we first find in government mathematics
in the micro size but there is many many
phenomenas uh feeds cannot be captured
by the determinism or the classical
probability Theory so I think the Korea
or something is just some kind
yeah
example
yeah example yes
uh by the way maybe Daniel can you uh
replace this Quantum Consciousness with
the quantum Claudia yes so the quantum
concept has been used to you know uh
implied this Quantum brain hypothesis
which may be or you know potential you
know uh true but the sulfur
we don't really see the strong evidence
about you know this um particular thing
so
um
what's funny I I'm thinking of the
classic qualia question what is it like
to be a bat
and it's like
what if the like is interpreted as a
metaphor
um
[Music]
what if there's a metaphorical mapping
to bat which is an observer dependent
mapping amongst some Spates you know
among spaces
hmm
because we've moved the focus from the
the objective
Standalone
experience of the bat
to considering mappings
amongst cognitive systems one critical
one being for example whoever is
listening to the question and a bat
who's the one who actually answers that
question
yes
oh okay so you you asked also about the
you know the inspiration from the
category Theory uh relevant to the uh
issue of the metaphor right that was a
communication and in fact um so now it's
a bit you know far from this you know
our Quantum query and they jump back to
another topic but uh so the metaphor uh
model of a metaphor is something that
the hyatta has been working on so I'll
uh
yeah but the the other part which is
this you know communication
and that's something that we also wrote
together uh last year
um and using this you know concept uh
called an adjunction in a category
Theory which may be also interesting to
uh discuss so
2016 paper we already mentioned that
little uh category theory is a very
promising for the
um
study of Consciousness precisely because
it provides different levels of uh
sameness
when I heard this from hayato I was like
what what do you mean but you know as
simultaneously it makes a lot of sense
and in fact many many you know
controversy or you know confusion among
the you know field of Consciousness but
not only for Consciousness other fields
like ecology as well
like you know uh classification of the
animal species and things like that all
up there depends on this you know what
do you mean by the thing
together
right and this is uh something that also
relates to what you are talking about a
moment ago which is Observer dependence
right so in the uh at uh even at the
really very important
how it is you know our reality I think
that what matters is
some notion of this subjective choice of
what it means to be the same
equivalence or adjunction is a
particularly interesting kind of
situation where for example you know
um integer and the real number is
definitely different
but in terms of the relationship if you
start to think about the relationship
there is some kind of you know a
one-to-one correspondence between them
and also uh Hiatus book also written in
Japanese but uh recently I did it and
one of the interesting example is also
multiplication and exponentiation
they you know at the level the object or
number it doesn't you know match right
but there is a very nice relationship
between them that is very fundamental
and something like this you know
apparently completely different thing
but finding really
um meaningful relationship that's very
fundamental in communication you know we
are talking different kind of language
with different kind of meaning but
because when I say something you reply
and then there is some kind of
systematic difference
[Music]
between what I expect and what I hear
that's the kind of prediction era
um
right I think the prediction era may not
need to be minimized in fact but as long
as it's consistent and systematic
then it actually works as a you know
very nice translational kind of a device
like I don't I I continue you know after
living like 20 years more more than 20
years of living outside of Japan I still
have very strong English accent either
in Japanese or you know Japanese living
in Australia or you know you get a us I
can't minimize this prediction error
but because I have this systematic
prediction error for you you totally
understand me right
something like this is uh the uh
interesting thing about that Junction
well this this makes me think about uh
Nest is reference frames in
communication
and let's just say that the the expected
free energy or maybe even the integrated
information content is such and such a
level
but it varies within some range it's 100
plus or minus 10. instead of just trying
to naively minimize that to zero
we can create a nested
model such that we expect that to be 100
plus or minus 10. at which point the
non-zero value is stabilized or buffered
and so then that becomes
the
kind of stabilizes or wraps
the fact that we're not
perfectly
transmitting information but we can be
perfectly aligned that we're not
perfectly transmitting information
and also our language understanding for
fluent speakers
were able to map the phonemes
a little bit deeper we're able to read
between the lines or listen between the
phonemes so that people who say words
differently
map to the exact same
syntax let alone the semantics
the sound gets kind of abstracted out
but it influences our qualia
so something is being passed forward
with like
tonality and the timing and I wonder
about with of course large language
models how much context they're able to
Garner
from the string of tokens
when for our experience uh sending and
receiving natural language communication
it's all about
the timing and the tone and the setting
and so finding ways that we can describe
that type of information
the the category Theory capacity for the
different levels of sameness seems like
exactly the tool that we need
um
I have to do you want to add anything
yeah I'm thinking about but
[Music]
um
about that you know I have the
multi-level kind of free energy
I I actually have a question to you
actually so I recently uh discussed uh
with a roboticist in Japan uh June Tani
yeah do you know his work
yes yeah is uh using this predictive
coordinating kind of scheme uh for um
constructing the set of you know
autonomous robot and uh he thinks this
you know uh intermingo of the top down
prediction and the bottom-up you know a
prediction error is a place that you
know Korea emerges and things like that
but one one of the things you know most
interesting uh aspect of that his model
to me is that he has this different time
scale for his uh neural system
[Music]
the most peripheral mortal ml1 the
sensory level has a very fast you know
time scale so that tries match with you
know what how what's happening outside
and then uh uh what they want to do
towards you know outside and the
intermediate level has a slightly longer
kind of you know time scale so there is
some kind of inertia and an even higher
level has a much much longer time scale
and uh
so in DL probably neural system there is
also different level of the time scale
are the different levels of the
mechanism are acting at the same time
like um changing the activity state in
our spiking or not and also released all
the synapses uh uh synaptic transmitters
that could increase the uh decrease over
the time and also even the new neurons
emerging and are going out so
um the the minimization where you are
talking about minimization probably that
kind of minimization is actually
happening independently and also
coherently potential or contradictory
across different levels another regions
and there may be some kind of effort or
whatever to also you know coordinate
this kind of contradictory demands of
the minimization
we think about this issue do you still
think
it's an uh useful way to think about
or use the term minimization in this
situation
yeah it's a great question well one
thing
that stood out to me was you described
the slower moving levels as having
inertia and from the Bayesian mechanics
perspective that's exactly how we would
model it they're slower moving they have
more inertia and they move more like
classical objects whereas the faster
time scales are moving more like lighter
particles more like that Quantum probe
in the limit
and then this sort of Center
or the highest nested model would be
like the most cognitively massive
potentially the slowest potentially
integrating information over the longest
time window
and certainly this is uh underlaying by
these multiple time scales a mechanism
spiking neurons from a few hundred
milliseconds time scale
neuromodulatory processes over seconds
and minutes synaptic plasticity even
neurogenesis and and are the development
of our brain so what does it really mean
that minimization is occurring when we
have this heterarchy where we have
similar types of free energy minimizing
units or active inference units within a
level like cortical columns or grid cell
units and then also we have these nested
models that are optimizing across
uh spacious temporarily separated scales
well one paper that looked at this was
our livestream 42 on the slam
simultaneous localization and mapping
also in robotics and so they had a two
uh nested model with two steps and the
lower level was like the tactics and
that was where you had the motor and the
sensors and then the nested model was
slower that was like where do I want to
be that was more like the strategy and
um
you can create an expected free energy
functional that sums across those two
levels
[Music]
how you tune the parameters
is going to
matter
because
how do you wait yeah yeah
um like and one one this comes up with
like preference learning like if you
have if your preference if you have two
left or turn and right turn and your
preference Vector is like two and one
versus two million and one million
then that is the ratio of the preference
is the same but the amplitude of the
preferences is a lot different which is
going to swing the model towards valuing
pragmatic outcomes whereas if you had
0.02 and 0.01 the ratio of the
preference would still be the same but
it's such a small amplitude preference
and so similarly with expected free
energy minimization it's
you could make it so that
the The Joint minimization was driven by
just the top level of the model
and then this sort of contradictions or
even increases in expected free energy
of the lower sensory model would
basically always be accepted in service
of the top model or vice versa
and it seems like biological systems
with their sort of precarious or
self-organized criticality
um
operations they're poised where you can
have like propagations
where small changes in the bottom up
model can propagate
and um and induce like phase changes of
higher levels and vice versa so they're
certainly poised parametrically at a
special place where the composition
of the faster sensory motor models and
the slower like cognitive or narrative
or metacognitive levels it's all poised
in a very integrated way potentially
even one that is um where where the IIT
measures tell us something useful
um
but yes the the contradictory demands
of subunits within a level of collective
behavior and across levels
as a biologist I think we just point to
ecology Evolution and developments and
just distributed systems that don't
exist at an Adaptive point
or Implement adaptive Dynamics amidst
uncertainty they just fail to exist and
so the complex biological systems that
we observe today do manage that
trade-off and then in robotics they have
this unique challenge of developing
systems
with one shot or with iterated
development that do have some of those
properties but for sure there's no
reason to think that just by laying out
a nested active inference model
that you would actually get like a more
adaptive decision-making agent in fact
as you Nest models the state space these
models becomes vast and with some back
of the envelope calculations you can see
like well if I do this level of nesting
and have this kind of sensor array
we need this absurd amount of data to
actually parameterize this model and by
the time we collected that many
observations maybe the causal
structure that we learn to the world you
know 200 hours of video ago don't apply
yeah
I mean that that could be a quite a huge
difference between uh probably IIT and
the free energy I I think um the IAD
explicitory states that the decimal time
scale that matters
but in this in this case it's uh just
about you know Korea is our particular
time scale that maximize integrated
information
and that corresponds to the time scale
of our experience
you know model you know that
um slowest uh
time scale is like on the order of 100
seconds or something like that and also
you know new synaptic plasticity is on
the order of hours and uh most likely
spiking neurons seems to be more
mattering with respect to our particular
experience at each moment right and the
why it is the case
um that the provisional answer provided
by ID is at the because at that
particular time scale integrated
information is much more
and across the scale and across the
regions but um this is a huge conjecture
and nobody knows whether this is true or
not and uh when we use the fly model uh
we weren't we uh we weren't able to sort
of confirm any kind of a clear peak in
the integrated information
um using a different time scale so it's
still you know something that I'm very
interested in um looking but uh
still not uh clear whether this is the
case I don't know if hayato has um some
um idea or
um inside into the appropriate time
scale for Consciousness or something
from the physics point of view
yeah yeah yeah I have some Souls that
maybe that it becomes a long story so uh
and also connects to the
um Observer dependence uh problem so I I
was thinking thinking about how to
explain this very important things in
one stress and I found that
first
um the very uh simple fact that there is
no uh uh
there comes no identically same two
events uh every event is different in
some respect
but uh to do science or more General is
some recognition of law we need some the
Criterion of sameness
for example
you want to know how to feed at how to
heal the disease
uh you should identify the different
persons people as the same same kind of
uh the samples or something
of course there is no identical
persons but you should you have to uh
the identify the the same in the members
of the same group something so all the
scientific studies is depend on some
choice of the sameness and so in that
sense all the science depends on this
kind of choice or the sameness uh as you
both
pointed out and uh there is no I think
that there is no canonical choice of the
Samus you can choose every semeness but
if you choose some sameness then uh you
can talk about The observables Observers
means some kind of quantities you can
observe or something
maybe it's randomly change the value or
no value like a count of case but by
measuring process it it's become half
the value or something so so they always
may be indefinite uh nature of the such
kind of quantities but
anyway the the we can imagine that
quantities has some kind of structure
between the quantities so it in
mathematical terms it it will be some
the algebra of the observables
then how to connect these ideas
theoretical idea to the experimental uh
thing is the key is expectation value so
uh Theory provides expectation value of
something and we can connect the theory
and the experience experiments by
comparing the theoretical expectation
value and average of samples so all the
quantitative science depends on this
structure like algebra observous and
some mapping from the observables
algebra to the sum number system so this
is called the state it is in mathematics
and algebra and state is something like
the mapping of quantities of random
variables or observables into its
expectation value so this mapping over
expectation is technically called state
so if you start start from Observer
algebra and state this is a starting
point of non-commutative probability
theory that is if this algebra is
commutative then the conventional
probability is probability Theory can
reconstruct from this commutative
algebra and the state but if this is
non-commutative as now pointed out if
the process is
essential then these algebra should be
non-commutative then we have the uh
[Music]
mathematics or something so in this case
The Observer dependence uh is described
uh uh the the other kind of Observer
dependence can be described because uh
you don't you can't have the classical
probability space for the old always
always but if you choose one observables
one observable like position or momentum
you could you can choose this then you
can construct the classical probability
space so the choice of context or a
choice of measuring something is by
choosing something so context you can
have the classical kind of reality
so this Observer this kind of Observer
with dependence is where formulated by
using non-commutative probability space
so I think the these multi-layered
observable uh
yeah uh Observer dependence is uh it can
be described by using non-commutative
probability
other the last thing I would say is the
connection of the category Theory
unknown commutative probability uh very
interestingly if the category category
is given like a causal system called
causal system give us some category like
a causalization is Arrow and the
composition is a is called b b equals c
then
indirectly of course at least they call
C or something so that it becomes a it
can be considered as a category there is
many many kind of category but if the
category is given then uh the the
algebra refracting this categorical
structure it is necessary
non-commutative uh if that there is a
non-trivial arrow between two options so
probability is from the mathematical
point of view it's kind of uh
the two aspects of the same thing like
the fundamental observe of the
dependence or contextual dependence or
something and this contextuality like a
top in top of theory the actually this
choosing Concepts and the transformation
between the context can be uh
formulated in terms of topos which is a
very powerful uh kind of category so
sorry for the too long explanation but
uh without that this very fundamental
question it cannot be organized sorry
for the long long explanation
oh it's it's awesome I mean empirically
if you have a sensor that's getting
measurements at a certain time scale
then there's a binding of the time scale
of the of the Observer and the
processing
um can I ask a question from the chat
all right Dave asks
at one time Professor tanini was
representing the shape of the relations
between complexity and Consciousness
such that two richly connected systems
are non-conscious
they're overwhelmed by the complexity
recently the inverted U that shows this
relation seems to have become scarce
leading to undue confusion
have IIT people abandoned the idea that
there is a bounded sweet zone for
Consciousness can a system be either too
simple or too complex to act consciously
so is IIT lead us to a kind of monotonic
Consciousness concept or could there be
a U-shaped relationship with information
integration and qualia
I see yeah I can all see the comment
here
[Music]
um
right there
so the Indian the question is can the
system be either too simple or too
complex to act consciously right in the
sense yeah
from an IIT point of view uh
there are several things that uh needs
to be said uh
but I inverted you is still there in a
sense and uh here
this person seems to be confusing
between the axis of that kind of
complexity
and the axis of the connectedness
you know in IIT original formulation and
it's still the true for the IIT 4.0
which is the latest one uh when the
system is too connected let's say if you
have uh you know 100 neurons and each of
them are connected to everybody
and in a uniform way then uh uh IIT
predicts that you know there it doesn't
have much you know uh
uh complexity or compositionality or you
know uniqueness to arise from that kind
of you know system and uh you know even
if you cut the system
um it doesn't matter much and so that
would lead to uh most likely
um very low level of consciousness
um
I think that's what yes I should have
typed connectivity yes yeah
if that's the case that's fine but
higher complexity
which is granted by some small world or
some sparse connectivity structure
higher complexity is monotonically
associated with more consciousness
it's not the case in IIT and that is
true from the beginning and the uh
easiest kind of you know example is to
have a two highly complex kind of system
that is uh Loosely connected between
them
you know it's a kind of a situation
where you are interested right in a
sense like and Colony yeah each Aunt has
a huge brain you know even though it
looks extremely small the number of the
neurons they have is more than one
medium right I think in that order yes
around a million yeah so I think
naturally predicted you know the causal
connection or
um integrated information arising from
this one million neurons within my ants
are going to be really massive it's very
difficult to disconnect in any way uh in
uh in your uh meaning of a full way
however interaction between a single and
to the another has a much less direct
causal relationship
and therefore the local Minima
or local Maxima of the five value is
going to be very huge within each and
but when you combine or when you treat
all these lots of ants it looks it
definitely does you know bring some kind
of intelligent and complex kind of you
know Behavior but phenomenality is not
there at that level
phenomenality Consciousness
within this in a maximum level of you
know integrated information like pretty
much like you know what we talked about
in time scale stuff you know we have a
huge you know complex and you know very
intelligent kind of behavior and
artifacts in the long time scale and
there's a short time scale but what
matters for our phenomenology is this
particular several orders of 100
milliseconds
that corresponds to the maximum of the
integrated information
so you still have emergent intelligence
at the colony level
but that doesn't necessarily mean that
you have qualia arising at that level
for analogous reasons why our qualia are
at the spiking time scale despite that
being only one of the nested time scales
exactly exactly
intelligence and Consciousness qualia is
completely uh you know dissociable
and that you know leads to you know the
commentary about the large language
model probably right
is probably structurally built to be
very simple
most almost like probably you know
cerebellum in the human brain which
accounts roughly like 80 percent of our
neurons in the brain
you know out of uh 10 to the 11 neurons
in the brain you know eighty percent are
in the cerebral but even if you you know
remove it or you know lose it or born
without it it seems you know
Consciousness is not that different
and that's
uh and a simple kind of prediction that
you know cerebellum is doing maybe
something similar to the you know large
language model is doing
it's very modular it's parallel it's not
integrated it does a lot of intelligent
things but nothing to do with
consciousness
[Music]
very interesting
well maybe in our closing sections
um of course anything you want to share
or ask but
how does active inference
benefit and grow from what you're
sharing and how do you see things
unfolding for people interested in these
topics
do you want to say something first yeah
I was thinking um okay
then uh from my and um so I used to
um have difficulty in uh you know
thinking about the uh active inference
or Monica blanket and things like that
but you know by broadening my
perspective and so becoming more
generous I I started to feel like more
uh maybe some aspects of the thinking
and also former formulation can be
uh
yeah relevant at least you know for the
explanation of the biological systems in
a various domain and if uh it's uh also
you know useful to explain intelligence
or construct intelligence that would be
great
and uh from our work of the quantum
quality of hypothesis if a quarter is
something that is influenced by its
measurement then that aspect maybe you
know emphasizing this uh usually you
know cordial Consciousness is kind of
considered a passive
you know a construct like at the given
moment what I'm experiencing starting
passive but now I'm more thinking about
because of this you know collaboration
with the heart and other people that
can't be the case and it's more to do
with the process that's a process it may
not be that kind of the level of the
active inference that you're thinking
like you know not the level of the
acting on the world
but more to do with that this state
itself influencing itself might be some
kind of you know important uh insight to
understand the quality
um
okay I
I my comment is the uh
okay so the it is uh related to the
concept of States again because uh
expectation value I I pointed out the
importance of expectation value but uh
for example what is the expectation
value for the for example the cause
strength of causality or something then
the problem of time scale is very
important so the you can uh course grain
the for example the brain activity for
the one time scales another time scale
so I think if IID is correct there is a
good time scale which is important of
importance regulating importance of the
choosing the uh this uh structure then I
think the brain information or something
called causal structure should be the
good category and you can construct a
non-commutative algebra and State is
defined or something so the time scale
is quite fundamental and
on the other hand
the state on the category as that is a
state on the category algebra can be uh
uh represented by some kind of weight on
arrows the positive kind of weight on
arrows so the changing the state is a
change in the weight of these hours the
positive definite functions I think this
the transition of the weighting of the
uh this arrow is very uh from at least
mathematically very interesting to
compare the active inference uh as a
mathematical point of view so good uh
wait wait to the better weight or
something is very hard to say the
uh interesting to compare I I'm not uh I
don't have much knowledge about active
inference but it seems to me it is quite
useful to connect this level the state
change or something so yeah it is very
uh interesting for me and
um
other other thing is
I forgot the south point but
yeah so
yeah yeah and yes uh as now already
uh okay points out the
I I talked about the measurements
instruments but the point of the this uh
notion is a probe system so measurement
is always uh
often considered as a very uh direct
kind of interaction like the system and
the environment but environment has some
kind of rope into the system then the
interaction is occurred with this Pro
Band this system I think it is very
analogous to the quoria the case of so
of course the outer world is relating to
the brain inside of course at least
process over the historically or
developmentally but I think the this
power through perception was something
the brain has its probe over the world
for example this interaction is very
hard to say in interesting so
measurement the analogy to the
measurement Theory may be that some
physically within the brain but some
kind of
probe of the outer system under this
Korea is interacting so I think the it
unifies the picture I think
maybe
what do you think now for example yeah
yeah so that's actually very much uh
related to what I was actually
constructing this morning
yeah so I was reading uh this Ozawa as a
paper that describes the instrument
and I I now I'm getting better
understanding what it means but what he
says is that every observable a of a
system s is identified with the
observable a tensored with the
instrument I of a system S Plus S Prime
so s here is the original system and S
Prime is the one that with any system s
uh x s Prime external to s
and what the height was meaning is that
this S Prime is a probe system which is
a part of the environment right yeah
and so here what this uh you know
Quantum uh initials
system description but it's also true
for the quantum combination and in my
case it is also true for the quantum
Courier hypothesis is that uh some kind
of query experiencing system is
interacting with the word
but through the sort of membrane or sort
of the like Mark of bracket like thing
which is already filtering this is a
large interaction of other sensory input
and attention
and this part itself is kind of you know
interacting with itself yeah these
arrows are
uh the critical part and then if we
translate that you know otherwise our
way to in our case this could cause not
every coil a of a core experiencing
system s
which is uh in the case of IIT it's
called a complex Observer a times
instrument over system S Plus S Prime
and this S Prime here I think will
include all the neuronal processes that
support the underlying yeah
but it doesn't really necessarily
directly in the external environment oh
yeah you know many people start to do
that but you know if you do that then
suddenly you know hallucination or
dreaming and things like that becomes
very difficult to expand yeah yeah it's
including too much
[Music]
yeah I think that corresponds to what
you wanted to say right I guess exactly
exactly
yeah
well this is really awesome I very much
appreciate that we could have this
conversation is there anything else you
want to add or ask
yeah thank you I also enjoyed and uh it
was also good for me to formulate my
thoughts as well
yeah I'm very surprised uh yeah
surprised me in the
um
how consistent uh our thoughts are so
how to say that it's it was just a
surprise for me
um maybe uh the conversation often goes
how to say diverse but our conversation
has a very surprisingly the conversion
so I think it's quite interesting in
itself and yeah I run I learned much
from this conversation and thank you for
inviting us
thank you so much so
hope to uh join on your channel and hear
updates on your research as things
develop so thank you again
thank you thank you
bye-bye bye-bye